hey aush students here's period 8 in
Just 4
[Music]
minutes period 8 spans from 1945 to 1980
after World War II America experienced a
period of prosperity with the passage of
the GI Bill families grew and moved into
suburbs like lown Conformity and
consumerism were the norm with husbands
who commuted to work on Eisenhower's
interstate system while wives bought the
latest consumer appliances and cared for
the family but Young Americans rebelled
against Conformity like the Beats this
coincided with the developing Cold War
which was a period of tension between
the United States and the Soviet Union
at home Americans feared communism
during a second Red Scare this hystero
was driven by the house and Americans
Activities Committee and senator Joseph
McCarthy as well as the convictions of
aler his and the rosenbergs meanwhile
Cold War foreign policy centered on
containing communism which was first
proposed in George kennan's Long
Telegram this was seen through the
Marshall Plan the Truman Doctrine and
the Eisenhower Doctrine the Eisenhower
Administration also used brinkmanship to
deter Soviet aggression later policy
include Kennedy's less aggressive
flexible response while Nixon's dayon
sought to ease tensions there are a few
critical Cold War events that you want
to know the first challenge was the
Berlin blockade and the Berlin airlift
in 1948 America responded to the Soviet
blockade of Berlin by airlifting
supplies to West berliners and the
Korean War which was fought between 1950
and 1953 is important because it was the
first proxy war of the Cold War it
showed that both sides were willing to
go to war over their ideals even if it
was indirect and the Cuban Missile
Crisis is the closest America and the
Soviet Union were to an allout nuclear
war after Americans discovered the
installation of Soviet missiles in Cuba
Kennedy and kushev were able to
negotiate a diplomatic solution which
help thaw tensions the Vietnam War also
occurred in periodate out of fear of a
domino effect in Asia Eisenhower and
Kennedy first sent military advisers but
both refused to send combat troops this
changed after the Gulf of tonen incident
when President Johnson sent 500,000
American troops within 4 years the war
was met with heavy opposition at home as
the counterculture movement protested
the draft and families saw the war from
their televisions events like the melee
Massacre and the publishing of the
Pentagon papers also increased Americans
distrust in the government the Civil
Rights Movement also gained momentum in
the 1950s and 1960s the movement saw
early victories like the brown be the
Board of Education case in the
Montgomery Bus Boycott which was started
by Rosa Parks groups like Martin Luther
King Jr's Southern Christian leadership
conference and the Student Nonviolent
Coordinating Committee fought for
equality through marches demonstrations
and sens and after being arrested in
1963 King wrote the famous letters from
A Birmingham Jail where he stressed the
importance of Civil Disobedience and
these tactics were successful leading to
the passage of the Civil Rights Act in
1964 and the Voting Rights Act in 1965
but some opposed the slow pace of the
movement like Malcolm X and the Black
Panthers who supported more direct
confrontation and black nationalism
while Johnson oversaw new civil rights
legislation he also implemented new
programs to combat poverty Johnson's
Great Society established Medicare medic
project Head Start and other programs
for lowincome families but like the New
Deal it met resistance over increased
government spending and providing
welfare the success of the Civil Rights
Movement inspired other groups to fight
for change Betty freedan published The
Feminine Mystique inspiring women to
challenge traditional gender Norms she
also helped establish the National
Organization for Women and pushed for an
equal rights amendment but some
conservatives like Phyllis Schley
opposed the bill and fought to maintain
traditional gender roles Latino
Americans fought for equality with the
Cho movement and C Chavez with the
United Farm Workers Association while
Native Americans fought with
organizations like the American Indian
movement and while lgbtq plus groups
advocated for safety and equality they
saw little changes as demonstrated by
The Stonewall riots another movement to
know is the environmentalist movement
which was inspired by Rachel Carson's
book Silent Spring she exposed the use
of damaging pollutants and chemicals
like DDT this inspired the creation of
the Environmental Protection Agency and
the passage of the Clean Air Act and the
Clean Water Act it also led to the
Celebration of America's first Earth day
period 8 ends with Jimmy Carter's
Administration even though he
successfully negotiated the Camp David
Accords Carter was criticized for a weak
economy because of continued stagflation
and for his failure to negotiate the
release of American hostages in Iran
thanks for watching and if you want more
aush helps like study guides timelines
and summary videos make sure you check
out the ultimate review packet